<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-25T01:40:46-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">[Mind From Matter]</title><subtitle>Seeking the mind by looking at the brain. Posts about me, computational neuroscience, cognitive science, and life.</subtitle><author><name>Richard Gao</name></author><entry><title type="html">First post!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/test-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First post!" /><published>2018-02-09T21:01:15-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-09T21:01:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/test-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/test-post/">&lt;p&gt;Hi, my name is Bob.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bold-testing&quot;&gt;bold testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al. what is going on I don’t know markdown et al.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Richard Gao</name></author><category term="holas" /><summary type="html">A unique line of text to describe this post that will display in an archive listing and meta description with SEO benefits.</summary></entry></feed>